מזל טוב Mazel tov חודש טוב. chodesh tov. Today's דף daf is
ל"ו. lamed-vav. We pick up on ל"ו עמוד ב', lamed-vav amud bet,
after ל"ז, lamed-zayin, excuse me, 37, just as I was saying. 7-7
is today. We pick up on ל"ו עמוד ב' lamed-vav amud bet
at the bottom third after the parenthesis. So we had just analyzed
a whole משנה mishna about an ox that gores multiple times, how
it gets divided amongst the different people whose property was damaged. The
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael debate. And now
we actually turn, the last analysis has really very little to do
with this משנה mishna per se. Let's take a look. תנן התם,
Tenan hatam, we taught over there later on in החובל. Hachovel. התוקע
לחבירו, Hatokeia lachaveiro, if somebody like either yells in his friend's ear
or more likely means like hits his friend near the ear or
something. רש"י Rashi says near the ear or something.
I don't know.
Anyway, נותן לו סלע, Notein lo sela, you give him a סלע.
sela. That's the assessment for בושת, boshet, for the embarrassment and the
shame. That's if there's any damages like loss of hearing, hospital bills
or whatever, that would be separate. But this is what the משנה
mishna assumes is the standard amount for בושת. boshet. רבי יהודה אומר
משום רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Yose HaGlili, מנה.
maneh. A מנה. maneh. Now a סלע sela is normally four זוז
zuz and a מנה maneh is 100 זוז. zuz. So already it
is pretty interesting that רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili assesses it
at 25 times what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma has. תוספות Tosafot
says that maybe the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma was talking about the
minimum or like the standard בושת boshet for a poor person or
person of low social standing, and רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili
is talking about a person of high social standing. But be that
as it may, that is not our focus. Okay, here, what is
our focus? So let's take a look. ההוא גברא דתקע לחבריה. Hahu
gavra detaka lechavrei. So a certain person who hit, banged his friend,
slapped his friend on the ear. So you were going to apply
the law of this משנה. mishna. רש"י Rashi is immediately bothered that
we don't do בושת boshet in בבל Bavel because בושת boshet is
a קנס. knas. So רש"י Rashi says we're talking about some case
about תפס, tofas, it's not clear that that's true, but okay, anyway.
שדריה רב טוביה בר מתנא, Shachrei Rav Tuvia bar Matna, I wouldn't,
שדריה רב טוביה בר מתנא לקמיה דרב יוסף. Shachrei Rav Tuvia bar
Matna lakamei deRav Yosef. So רב טוביה בר מתנא Rav Tuvia bar
Matna sent the case in front of רב יוסף Rav Yosef and
he asked the following question: סלע צורי תנן Sela Tzoridnan או o
סלע מדינה תנן? Sela Medinan tnan? When it says a סלע, sela,
which is four זוז, zuz, does that mean סלע צורי, sela Tzori,
which is the sort of what we would sort of say the
standard, רש"י Rashi right,
the standard sort of a way of identifying the value of coins,
or סלע מדינה? sela Medina? סלע מדינה, sela Medina, it's very confusing,
you know, because they would use the same names for things but
there would be like two different systems. And סלע מדינה sela Medina
would be an eighth of סלע צורי. sela Tzori. So if there's
a half of a זוז zuz in a סלע מדינה, sela Medina,
four זוז zuz in a סלע צורי. sela Tzori. Okay, so רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says, just so you know, רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says מנה, maneh, okay, הגלילי HaGlili says מנה,
maneh, which means 100, okay, and who was the תנא קמא? Tanna
Kamma?
It doesn't say רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, no,
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Okay, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says סלע.
sela. Now סלע sela is normally said to be four זוז, zuz,
okay, זוז, zuz, but that's if we're talking about צורי, Tzori, okay.
The basic principle is that מדינה Medina is one eighth of סלע
צורי. sela Tzori. So it's a half of a זוז, zuz, which
is crazy, it's like a 200 times difference between the two. Anyway,
that's his question. Okay, yeah, exactly. Okay, that's the question. So,
אמר ליה תניתוה, amar lei tanituha, so we learned it. Where did
we learn it? We can infer it from our משנה mishna about
the goring ox. How is that?
ושנים הראשונים דינר זהב. Veshnayim harishonim dinar zahav. Okay, remember it has
a case about the ox that was being divided and it was
being divided 100, 50, 25, 25. Now that's a דינר זהב. dinar
zahav. A דינר זהב, dinar zahav, a gold דינר, dinare, is 25
times a דינר dinar is the same as a זוז, zuz, okay,
but a דינר זהב dinar zahav is 25 and a דינר כסף,
dinar kesef, a זוז, zuz, is one. All right, fine. Now what
does that prove? Okay, let's take a look. ואי סלקא
דעתך תני תנא סלע מדינה, Ve'i salka daitach tani tanna sela Medina,
if you think the תנא tanna of the משנה mishna would ever
be using the coinage of סלע מדינה, sela Medina, right, because we
always assume that the תנא tanna when he, because it's a question,
what did the משנה mishna mean when it said סלע? sela? Does
the standard coinage referred to in the משנה mishna mean סלע צורי
sela Tzori or סלע מדינה? sela Medina? So he is saying if
the תנא tanna would be prepared to use a סלע מדינה, sela
Medina, if that's what something a תנא tanna would refer to, so
נפלוג וניתני, niflog ulistniveiziv, I'm sorry, נפלוג וניתני niflog ulistni עד תריסר
וסלע. ad tresar vesela. So why not talk about let's say the
ox gored again. So what would happen if the ox would gore
again? It would be 100... Right, it would be a how would
it be
50 how would it be it would be 100
then 25
am I getting this
right
125 no all right 100 50
25 12 and a half 12 and a half did I get
that right or did I make a mistake here? 25 25 no
that's right. Okay fine. So if it gored again okay like this
is 200 that's 200. Okay. If it gored again that's how it
would break down okay because the last guy would get 200 and
then you'd divide the remaining 100 amongst all of these okay? So
why didn't the תנא Tanna give that example? So the assumption is
the תנא Tanna didn't give that example. This would be זוז Zuz
right this is a דינר זהב Dinar Zahav this is a זוז
Zuz which is a דינר כסף. Dinar Kesef. Okay. So why didn't
the תנא Tanna give that example? Because the presumption is he doesn't
want to be talking in halves. You only want to be talking
in whole units. But if you could refer to something called a
סלע Sela and that would mean a סלע מדינה Sela Medinah which
would be a half of a זוז Zuz you'd have a way
to refer to it. You could say 12 זוז Zuz and a
סלע. Sela. Everybody got me? Yes? No? Sort of? Okay.
Right. So you could say 12 זוז Zuz and a סלע. Sela.
So the fact that you didn't shows that you would never talk
in סלע מדינה Sela Medinah language. So you could talk about a
סלע Sela which is four זוז Zuz you could talk about a
זוז Zuz but you could never talk about if you needed to
say half זוז Zuz you have to say a half זוז. Zuz.
You would never be able to say a סלע. Sela. And we
don't want to talk about halves. So the fact that we didn't
do this shows we because we don't want to talk about halves
shows that
we could never use the word of a סלע מדינה. Sela Medinah.
Okay.
Exactly. If you're in צור Tzur the only way you can get
a half is by saying a half. But if you're in מדינה
Medinah you can get a half זוז Zuz by talking about a
סלע. Sela. You're in צור. Tzur. Okay so it sounds like this.
Okay. Well anyway okay. So תני תנא סלע מדינה Tani tanna sela
medinah ואי סלקא דעתך תני תנא סלע מדינה ve'ei salka da'atach tani
tanna sela medinah ניפלוג וניתני אטרייסר וסלע. niflog v'nisne atrei sar ve'sela.
Say 12 זוז Zuz and a סלע. Sela.
So presumably we didn't say that because we don't want to be
talking about halves which means that we'll never talk about סלע מדינה.
Sela Medinah. אמר ליה Amar leh so the response back was תנא
כי רוכלא ליתני וליזל? tanna ki rochla lisne v'leizel?
What the תנא Tanna like a merchant is going to go and
announce all of its wares? So okay what does it have to
give you it has to give it gave you this case. It
has to give you every single possible possibility keep on breaking it
down to more and more and more cases? It stopped after like
four gored oxen. You don't need five or six gored oxen. Okay.
מאי הויה לה? Mai havya lah? What was the conclusion about whether
the תנא Tanna ever refers to a סלע מדינה Sela Medinah or
not? פשטוה מהא דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב Pashku'ah me-had amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav from what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the
name of רב Rav כל כסף האמור בתורה כסף צורי kol kesef
amar ba-Torah kesef Tzuri whenever the תורה Torah talks about an amount
you pay like שלשים של עבד sheloshim shel eved or something like
that right that's שלשים כסף sheloshim kesef right so that anyway so
that is going to refer to סלע צורי Sela Tzuri not סלע
מדינה Sela Medinah סלע צורי Sela Tzuri ושל דבריהם כסף מדינה. v'shel
divreihem kesef Medinah. And when they but when there's a rabbinic obligation
we refer to כסף מדינה. kesef Medinah. So actually we will refer
to כסף מדינה kesef Medinah and סלע מדינה. Sela Medinah. So when
our משנה Mishna talked about the rabbis assessing the value of the
בושת boshet and they said סלע Sela if you're talking about not
sometimes identifying of a תורה Torah value but you're talking about a
rabbinic assessment you know some type of a rabbinic fixed fine or
rabbinic assessment then we're going to be talking in סלע מדינה Sela
Medinah terms. Okay so therefore yes we are talking about a half
of a זוז Zuz we are talking about סלע מדינה Sela Medinah
and there's a 200 time difference between them. Okay now. One minute.
אמר ליה ההוא גברא Amar leh ha-hu gavra so okay this guy
now it was determined owed a half of a זוז Zuz not
four זוז Zuz a half of a זוז. Zuz. So אמר ליה
ההוא גברא הא לאו פלגא דזוזא הוא? Amar leh ha-hu gavra holo
palga d'zuza hu? What it's a lousy half זוז Zuz that I'm
getting for getting my ear boxed in? So לא בעינא Lo ba'ina
who needs it? I don't want a half זוז. Zuz. ניתביה לעניים
Nitvi l'ani'im go give it to the עניים. ani'im. Give it to
צדקה. tzedakah. הדר אמר ליה Hadar amar leh you know then he
changes his mind. You know what he said? ניתביה ניהלי Nitvi nihali
you know what I changed my mind. Give it to me I
will take it. איזיל ואיברי בי נפשאי Izil v'ivri bi-nafshei let me
at least use it to go get better let me at least
use it to go to the doctor. Okay which is interesting because
if it's בושת boshet then why isn't he also being assessed for
like שבת shevet and ריפוי ripuy and whatever? Anyway אמר ליה רב
יוסף Amar leh Rav Yosef רב יוסף Rav Yosef said no too
late כבר זכו בה עניים. kvar zachu bei ani'im. Once you said
give it to the עניים ani'im then the עניים ani'im already essentially
took possession of it. Now how is that? It was in the
pocket of the מזיק. mazik. He never put it into the צדקה
tzedakah box. What made it just because you said those words what
made it magically become now the possession of the עניים? ani'im? ואף
על גב דליכא עניים הכא V'af al gav d'leka ani'im hacha and
even though there were no עניים ani'im it's not like your words
now transferred it like there's a standard עני ani in town and
you said give it to the עניים *aniim*, it's like you were
מקנה *makneh* it to that person. Maybe there's even no עניים *aniim*
in the town, so there's nobody to be מקנה *makneh* it to.
So how is it that your words now made it owned by
the עניים *aniim*? אמר הכא *Am hacha*, אמר צדקה tzedaka, עניים הכא
*Am tzadaka aniim hacha*, there's no עניים *aniim* around. אנן יד עניים
אנן *Anan yad aniim anan*, we, the rabbis, are זוכה *zoche* on
behalf of the עניים *aniim*. Now Rashi says it's not just in
general we the rabbis. If you look at Rashi, Rashi says רב
יוסף Rav Yosef, הוה גבאי *Rav Yosef Hava Gabbai*. רב יוסף Rav
Yosef, *Rav Yosef* was a גבאי צדקה tzedaka. *gabbai tzedakah*. And this
case came in front of רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*. What happens? It
said
he sent a question to רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*. Now, it still
doesn't mean that רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* had the money in his
pocket. רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* was the rabbi it was referred to,
but somehow since the case was being adjudicated by רב יוסף *Rav
Yosef*, and the guy, maybe the guy said this to רב יוסף
*Rav Yosef*, 'you know what, give it to the עניים *aniim*,' it
sounds like somehow those words were directed or in the presence or
to רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, then רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* somehow has
taken possession for behalf of the עניים *aniim*. It's still a little
funny because presumably the money is still in the pocket of the
מזיק mazik. *mazik*. So don't you need some act of physical taking
possession of it? Anyway, דאמר רב יהודה Rav Yehuda: *d'amar Rav Yehuda*,
how do you know that the rabbis can represent the interests of
the עניים *aniim*? דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל יתומים אינם צריכים פרוזבול
*D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel yesomim einam tzerichin pruzbul*. יתומים *Yesomim* don't
need a פרוזבול *pruzbul* for שמיטה *shmitta* to write their debts over
to the בית דין *beis din*. Why? Because what a פרוזבול *pruzbul*
would do is it would assign בית דין *beis din* the right
to collect the debt. But basically, we assume that בית דין *beis
din* always is taking care of the interests of the עניים *aniim*.
And here it would be יתומים *yesomim*, it's not exactly the same
as the עניים *aniim*, but presumably יתומים *yesomim* mean people that are
orphans that are young and can't take care of their own interests
and so on are in a similar situation as the עניים *aniim*,
poor, maybe at the margins of society, not taken care of and
so on. And we the בית דין *beis din* take care of
their interests. So therefore, we naturally assume the responsibility of collecting their
debts for them. And therefore you don't need a פרוזבול *pruzbul* to
hand over their debts to the בית דין *beis din*. וכן תני
רמי בר חמא יתומים אינם צריכים פרוזבול *Vechen tani Rami bar Chama
yesomim einam tzerichin pruzbul*. רבן גמליאל ובית דינו אביהם של יתומים היו
*Rabban Gamliel u'veiso aviahem shel yesomim hayu*. רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* and
his בית דין *beis din*, they were the fathers for the orphans.
They took over that responsibility, so that was like they already took
upon themselves the responsibility for collecting the debt on behalf of the
עניים *aniim*. Now, and therefore here too, again, it's like the עני
*ani* is here because the גבאי צדקה tzedaka. *gabbai tzedakah* is here.
Now, it's still not exactly clear because the money hasn't gone into
their possession. I'll talk about that in תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* in a
minute, but let's just end this with the following story. ההוא גברא
*Hahu gavra*, חנן בישא *Chanan Bisha*, you gotta love that name, חנן
*Chanan* the bad one, תקליה לההוא
גברא *takleh l'hahu gavra*.
I remember this name. He comes up a few times. He hit
a guy, apparently in the ear. אזל לקמיה דרב הונא *Azal l'gamei
d'Rav Huna*. He came to רב הונא *Rav Huna*. אמר ליה זיל
הב ליה פלגא דזוזא *Amar lei zil hav lei palga d'zuza*. So
we're ruling that a סלע sela. *sela* is a סלע sela? מדינה
*sela medina* and half a זוז zuz. *zuz*. He says to חנן
בישא *Chanan Bisha*, go give him a half זוז zuz,
*zuz*. הוה ליה זוזא מכה *Hava lei zuza maka*. So חנן בישא
*Chanan Bisha* had a זוז zuz, *zuz* that was a
worn out, rubbed down זוז zuz *zuz*. You ever get one of
those dollars that's been through the wash a hundred times or whatever?
So he was looking for somebody to split it for him and
no merchant wanted to take this lousy worn out זוז zuz *zuz*.
בעי למיתבי ליה מיניה פלגא דזוזא *Ba'ei l'meisvei lei minei palga d'zuza*.
He wanted to cash it in and give him a half a
זוז zuz. *zuz* out of this זוז zuz, *zuz*. ולא אישתקל ליה
*V'lo ishtakal lei*. Nobody would take it from him and change it
for him. So you know what? תקליה אחרינא *Takleh achrina*, so he
hit him again, ויהיב ליה *v'yahiv lei*. And he gave him the
whole. That's what you get if you only have to pay a
half זוז zuz. *zuz*, it's not worth it. So anyway, people are
not so protected, I guess boxing in people's ears was a common
occurrence. Now, now I want to talk about
two important points
that are raised by תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*. First, let's look at this
question about how he took possession for the עניים *aniim*. יד עניים
אנן *Yad aniim anan*. תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafos* says bottom of ל"ו עמוד
ב' *lamed vav amud bais*. ואם תאמר דלא יד עניים נמי מחייב
צדקה tzedaka באמירה *Ve'im tomar d'lo yad aniim nami mechayev tzedakah ba'amira*.
תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafos*
says, forget יד עניים *yad aniim*. If you say you're going to
give צדקה tzedaka. *tzedakah*, that becomes like a type of a נדר
neder. *neder* that should automatically obligate you. So who needs יד עניים
*yad aniim*? He can't back out. He said he was going to
give it as צדקה tzedaka *tzedakah*. דאמר פרק קמא דראש השנה ופיך
זו צדקה *D'amar perek kamma d'Rosh Hashanah v'fi'cha zu tzedakah*. ויש לומר
דכמו שאין אדם adam, מקדיש דבר שלא בא לעולם הכא נמי אין
אדם adam. נותן צדקה דבר שלא בא לעולם *Ve'yesh lomar d'kemo she'ein
adam makdish davar she'lo ba l'olam hacha nami ein adam nosen tzedakah
davar she'lo ba l'olam*. So the whole interesting comparison, obligating yourself in
צדקה *tzedakah* is like a נדר neder. *neder*, giving to צדקה *tzedakah*
is like being מקדיש *makdish*. So you can't be מקדיש *makdish* something
you don't own. So if you said give it to the עניים
*aniim* and you don't own it yet, you weren't paid yet the
half זוז zuz, *zuz*, you can't transfer it yet to the עניים
*aniim*. So what can your words do? If your words can't transfer
the money yet to the עניים *aniim*, what can they do? So
he says, וכשאמר נתנו לעניים הוי זה חוב כמו שלא בא לעולם
*u'ch'she'amar nesei l'aniim heavei zei chov k'mo she'lo ba l'olam*. The money
wasn't yet in his possession, so he can't yet transfer it to
the עניים *aniim*. וכן אם היה אומר נתנו להקדש לא היה הקדש
hekdesh, קונה *V'chen im haya omer nesei l'hekdesh lo haya hekdesh koneh*.
Similarly if he said let it be הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh*, that wouldn't
work, he doesn't own it yet. ונחזי *U'nechze*. מיהא שאם היה אומר,
but here's what he could do with his words, חוב זה לכשיבוא
לידי יהיה להקדש או לצדקה. Chov zeh lichsheyavo l'yadi yehei l'hekdesh o
litzdaka. If you accept upon yourself a personal obligation, right
you make a, as an appeal, I will give $100 to צדקה,
to הקדש, when I get this money I will give it to
צדקה. That becomes a personal obligation, that becomes a נדר. neder. And
that's when we say your words can obligate you. But you did
not want to say a personal obligation, I promise to give this
to צדקה. You tried through your words to transfer it, this shall
belong to צדקה right now, I'm trying to make it owned by
צדקה. If it's not in your possession, you don't have the ability
to do that with your words. So your words can create a
personal obligation for צדקה and for הקדש, but they can't transfer it
unless it's in your property. Okay, דומה שמתחייב משום נדר. Domeh she-mitchayev
mishum neder.
That you would obligate yourself like a נדר. neder אבל זה לא
אמר כן, Aval zeh lo amar kein, אלא אמר תנהו לעניים, ela
amar tnahu l'ani-im, ולא נדר. v'lo nadar. Okay,
so that's interesting in terms of the power of your words again,
what it still doesn't explain is how רבי Rebbi whoever it was,
רב יוסף, took possession of it if it was still in the
hands of the מזיק. mazik I don't know, maybe the מזיק gave
it over to רב יוסף, maybe that's what we're supposed to expect.
Yes, Dov.
I just want to make certain, because תוספות Tosafot says דומה שמתחייב
מטעם נדר. domeh she-mitchayev mitam neder.
I mean if it would have seen, it would seem.
It's not really a נדר.
neder No, דומה domeh means
like a נדר neder, when I say it that way.
No, well
if you're emphasizing the word דומה, domeh, I think תוספות Tosafos, means
like it would appear to me that. I think that's what the
word דומה domeh means there. It's not saying that it is an
obligation comparable to נדר which you also could have said, but it
is, that's the word כמו נדר. kmo neder. But the word דומה
domeh here does not mean it's analogous to נדר, I think he
means דומה לי, domeh li, it appears to me that, is the
point of that word דומה. domeh. Yes.
I'm just trying to figure out, there's an implicit recognition here that
the monetary units in the גמרא Gemara are different than the תורה.
Torah. Right. And yet it seems like is there something that they're
trying to preserve about the numbers described in the תורה Torah for
certain things?
Well,
yeah, I'm not sure exactly what you mean but I will tell
you, here's the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. The תורה Torah says, and
it gives me the opportunity to look at the next תוספות. Tosafos
The תורה Torah says for example that מוהר הבתולות mohar habetulot is
fifty כסף. kesef. Now כסף kesef there is referred to as a
סלע. sela Okay, so we normally assume that that means 200 זוז.
zuz. Fifty times four is 200 זוז, zuz right? But if that
was, because that's because it's חמור בתורה, chamor ba-Torah, right?
How do we know שקל, shekel, how do we know סלע?
sela, Right, so we assume that's not being said here. Right, we
assume that the שקל shekel is what we call the סלע and
then it's a סלע צורי, sela tzuiri, right? So yeah, there's like
a lot of these built-in assumptions. But the interesting thing is, is
that according to, now that's because the word fifty כסף kesef are
written in the תורה Torah and therefore it's fifty סלע, 200 זוז,
zuz. etc. But there's a debate in the גמרא Gemara in כתובות,
Ketubot, you might remember, whether כתובה דאורייתא דרבנן. ketubah d'oraita d'rabanan. So
even though the קנס knas of fifty כסף kesef is 200 זוז
zuz based on this גמרא, Gemara, a number of גאונים Geonim פוסקים
poskim or whatever, it was widely פסק'ן pasken in ספרד Sfarad that
כסף kesef is, that כתובה דרבנן ketuba d'rabanan and that the actual
amount of the כתובה ketubah is not 200 זוז zuz but is
25 זוז. Okay? That the fifty שקל shekel in the תורה, Torah,
in the תורה Torah it meant 200 זוז, but when we use
that as our model for כתובה דרבנן, ketuba d'rabanan, we're going to
interpret it as כסף מדינה kesef medina and make it worth 25
זוז. So actually in ספרד Sfarad the value of the כתובה ketubah
was one eighth the value of the כתובה ketubah in אשכנז, Ashkenaz,
because they did כסף מדינה kesef medina and not כסף צורי. kesef
tzuiri. And for them the 50 זוז, although it was written in
the תורה, Torah, if you think that כתובה ketubah is דרבנן, d'rabanan,
it became only 25, not 200. Now this תוספות, Tosafos we won't
read inside for the sake of time, this תוספות Tosafos says it
doesn't matter if כתובה דאורייתא דרבנן, ketubah d'oraita d'rabanan, it comes from
the word fifty כסף kesef in the תורה Torah and it's 200
זוז. And that by the way was something that the הרא"ש, haRosh,
because the הרא"ש, haRosh,
you know הרא"ש haRosh is always an interesting transitional figure. He comes
from אשכנז, Ashkenaz, he lives in ספרד. Sfarad. So he coming from
אשכנז Ashkenaz believed there's a whole debate whether כתובה דאורייתא דרבנן. ketuba
d'oraita d'rabanan. He believed that כתובה ketuba anyway was, so in ספרד
Sfarad they believed that כתובה ketuba was דרבנן. d'rabanan. But the language
of the כתובה ketuba in אשכנז Ashkenaz that we know we have
in our כתובות אשכנזיות ketubot ashkenaziyot is דחזי ליכי מדאורייתא. d'chazi lichi
mid'oraita. Now for the ספרדים Sfaradim in the room, Rabbi Dov, your
כתובה ketubah says דחזי ליכי, d'chazi lichi, they don't say מדאורייתא, mid'oraita,
right? But you, yeah, so דחזי ליכי d'chazi lichi so the הרא"ש
haRosh was bothered because he thought כתובה ketuba was דרבנן d'rabanan and
if כתובה ketuba is דרבנן d'rabanan why are we saying דחזי ליכי
מדאורייתא? d'chazi lichi mid'oraita? So he said no, no, no, they're not
חייב chayav in כתובה מדאורייתא ketuba mid'oraita but the use of the
phrase דאורייתא d'oraita is to signal that you use כסף צורי kesef
tzuiri and not כסף מדינה. kesef medina. So you're going to do
200 זוז and not 25 זוז. So that was the way the
הרא"ש... haRosh... bridged the gap, but in reality those that פסקן pasken
כתובה Kesuvah was דרבנן d'rabbanan basically felt that a כתובה Kesuvah was
25 זוז and if you felt כתובה Kesuvah was דאורייתא d'oraisa it
was 200 זוז and that's based on the discussion in this גמרא
Gemara and parallel discussions elsewhere. Okay, let's move on now. Now we
get to a whole fun section of the גמרא, Gemara, or at
least for one דף, daf, and again, these things get done and
then revisited, but for now we get to today's דף daf focuses
on the discussion of becoming a מועד muad and then maybe also
going back and becoming a תם. tam. You need to do it
three times to become a מועד, muad, so that seems straightforward enough.
Let's look at this משנה. Mishna.
שור שהיה מועד שזהו מועד למינו ואינו מועד לשאינו מינו: Shor shehaya
muad shehu muad l'mino v'eino muad l'sheino mino: for שור's shor מועד
muad for its genre, for goring other oxen, but not for other
things, sheep or goats or whatever. או מועד לאדם ואינו מועד לבהמה,
O muad l'adam v'eino muad l'behema, it's a מועד muad for goring
people and not for goring animals. או מועד לקטנים ואינו מועד לגדולים,
O muad l'ketanim v'eino muad l'gedolim, for goring small animals but not
big animals. את שהוא מועד לו משלם נזק שלם ואת שאינו מועד
לו משלם חצי נזק, Es shehu muad lo meshaleim nezek shaleim v'es
she'eino muad lo meshaleim chatzi nezek, the things that it has established
a pattern,
it'll pay
full, the things that it has not habituated for,
will pay half damage.
So that means it can gore a hundred times, it can gore
a chicken then a cat then a person then
a—Yeah, so we'll see all those in the גמרא. Gemara. Right, well,
we'll see because then you might deal with—you might abstract it. Okay.
אמרו לפני רבי יהודה: Amru lifnei Rabbi Yehuda: they said to רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, הרי זה מועד לשבתות ואינו מועד לחול, Harei zeh
muad l'shabbasos v'eino muad l'chol, let's say an animal happened to gore
on שבת Shabbos and not on the weekday. So what would be
the הלכה? halacha? So now presumably what they were asking him was—at
what point do we—this is the way I understand what's going on—they're
asking him how formalist are we? Like if there's no good reason
to explain why an animal would limit itself to goring on שבת
Shabbos and not on the weekday, but the reality was it just
so happened that three times it was on שבת. Shabbos. Will we
look at just the reality of what it did and define מועד
muad in those terms, or are we going to use a little
bit of a סברא sevara and say, yeah, it's true it was
שבת Shabbos three times but that's immaterial? So what's the story if
it did it שבת Shabbos three times? And he said, yeah, we're
formalists. אמר להם לשבתות משלם נזק שלם ולימות החול משלם חצי נזק.
Amar lahem l'shabbasos meshaleim nezek shaleim v'liyamos hachol meshaleim chatzi nezek. Yeah,
on שבת Shabbos you pay full and on the weekday the rest
of the time. Now,
okay, now so רש״י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafos I read the whole
question as how formalist are we? רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot are
not happy with saying we are complete formalists, like and therefore, let's
say because you could have said, let's say it gored three times
on a Tuesday. Maybe it's only מועד muad for Tuesdays. So רש״י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot, understand that actually his answer was שבת Shabbos
does make a practical difference. So if you look at רש״י, Rashi,
רש״י Rashi says,
ג׳ ימי שבתות, Gimmel yemei Shabbosos, לאחר שהועד לשבתות העבירו לפניו, l'achar
shehuad l'shabbasos he'eviru lefanav, I'm sorry, no, אינו מועד לימות החול, eino
muad l'yamos hachol, middle of the משנה רש״י. Mishna Rashi.
Oh no, I'm sorry, the very first רש״י, Rashi, like right at
the beginning of the משנה, Mishna, רש״י Rashi says הרי הוא מועד
לשבתות לפי שהוא בטל ממלאכה וזחה דעתו עליו. Harei hu muad l'shabbasos
lefi shehu batel mimmellacha v'zacha da'ato alav. It's got a day off
so he's bored, so he goes around goring, that's the problem, you
know, you give your oxen a day off, they start getting into
trouble. Okay, so תוספות Tosfos's says הרי הוא מועד לשבתות. Harei hu
muad l'shabbasos. תוספות says מפרש בירושלמי לפי שראה אותם
במלבושין נאים אחרים וחשובים בעיניו ואינם נכרים... mefaresh b'Yerushalmi lefi she-ra'ah osam
b'malbushin na'im acherim v'chashuvim b'einav v'einam nikkarim... ואינם נכירים...
v'einam nekkirim... no, ואינם נכירים. v'einam nekkirim. But?
I don't know what the first one is.
The last one is אינם
נכירים. einam nekkirim.
נכרים, Nochrim, I think it means. They're foreign. Because he doesn't recognize
them. ואינו מכירם, v'eino makiram, right. So therefore everybody's wearing all these
fancy clothes, that gets him all curious and riled up. Okay, fine.
So they understand that the answer is not a pure formalism, it
is שבת Shabbos during the weekdays, it's not a Tuesday as opposed
to a Wednesday. Now the last line of the משנה Mishna is
אימתי הוא תם? Eimasai hu tam? When would he become a תם
tam if he happened to gore on three שבתות? Shabbosos? מששיחזור בו
ג׳ ימי שבתות. Misheyachzor bo gimmel yemei Shabbosos. It's not enough that
he sees animals during the weekdays, he has to, you know, it's
sort of like what's a בעל תשובה? ba'al teshuva? The רמב״ם Rambam
says a בעל תשובה ba'al teshuva is that you're in the same
place in the same circumstances and you don't repeat the sin. So
the way you become
a—the שור shor does תשובה, teshuva, the שור shor reverts himself to
being a תם—is tam he's given three opportunities of the same circumstances
that he's habituated with and he doesn't react three times in a
row.
Okay, that's the
משנה. Mishna. Now same for
קטנים ketanim and גדולים. gedolim. Exactly. Exactly. Now we're going to have
a nice little debate of one letter in the משנה. Mishna. איתמר,
Itmar, it was taught. רב זביד אמר זה ואינו מועד תנן ורב
פפא אמר אינו מועד תנן. Rav Zevid amar zeh v'eino muad tnan
v'Rav Pappa amar eino muad tnan. Do you have the vav? Is
it descriptive or is it telling you the law? For let's start
with רב פפא. Rav Pappa. רב פפא Rav Pappa reads like this:
שור שהוא מועד למינו אינו מועד לשאינו מינו. Shor shehu muad l'mino
eino muad l'sheino mino. If a שור shor gored three oxen, then
it's not a מועד mu'ad for other things. You basically look at
what it did and you don't abstract, you don't generalize. If it
happened to do three times oxen, it's only for oxen. It's a
מועד למינו mu'ad le'mino and it's an אינו מועד לשאינו מינו. einu
mu'ad leshe'einu mino. Okay, that's what he says. You basically assume that
something is only a מועד mu'ad for the things that it has—you
have concretely established a pattern for. רב זיד Rav Zid says he
reads the ו. vav. It's descriptive. No, no, no, we're talking about
a שור shor that was a מועד למינו ואינו מועד לשאינו מינו.
mu'ad le'mino ve'einu mu'ad leshe'einu mino. A normal שור, shor, if it
gored three times, I don't care what it gored, it would be
a מועד mu'ad for everything. It has to actually do something to
become an אינו מועד לשאינו מינו, einu mu'ad leshe'einu mino, which would
mean is not only did it gore three times oxen, but it
looked at sheep for three times and didn't gore them. Okay? So
normally you assume that these things are generic. If they've established it
three times, they establish it for all animals, all people, all everything.
Okay, but it could become an אינו מועד einu mu'ad if it
encounters other things and doesn't react. All right, so this is a
very big difference of how to read the משנה. Mishnah. רב פפא
Rav Pappa reads it as—רב פפא Rav Pappa without the ו, vav,
אינו מועד לשאינו מינו einu mu'ad leshe'einu mino says it's only a
מועד mu'ad for what it's done. So
if it's never seen another sheep in its life, all it's seen
is oxen, it hasn't had an opportunity to not gore sheep, so
it doesn't matter. Once it gores—if it's only gored oxen, it's only
a מועד mu'ad for oxen.
So even if it gores a sheep, it only pays חצי נזק.
chatzi nezek.
Right. And רב זיד Rav Zid says, no, we assume it's a
מועד mu'ad for everything unless it demonstrates that it's not a מועד
mu'ad for those other things. Now, what's not clear is how often
would it have to demonstrate? Right? I said three times. But let's
say it wasn't three times. Let's say it saw a sheep once—it
gored an ox once, saw a sheep and didn't gore it, gored
an ox a second time, and saw a sheep and didn't gore
it, and gored an ox a third time. It didn't not gore
sheep three times. It only didn't gore sheep two times. But maybe
that's enough. You saw while it was goring oxen, it wasn't goring
sheep. Okay, so that's not fully spelled out. But basically, רב זיד
Rav Zid says you would normally just generalize. You'd have to have
evidence to say that it's not a מועד mu'ad for those other
things. Okay, now, רב זידא אמר ואינו מועד תנן. Rav Zida amar
ve'einu mu'ad tnan. It's the case it happens to not be a
מועד mu'ad for other things. הא סתמא, ha stama, the standard case
would הוי מועד. havei mu'ad. If it gores three times, we generalize,
and it's a מועד mu'ad for everything. רב פפא אמר אינו מועד
תנן. Rav Pappa amar einu mu'ad tnan. No, no, no, it's telling
you a הלכה. halakhah. It's not a מועד mu'ad for other things.
דסתמא לא הוי מועד. de'stama lo havei mu'ad. Even if it gores
three oxen, we just assume that's the only thing it's a מועד
mu'ad for. Okay.
Now we're going to see how they read it from the משנה.
Mishnah.
They just had different texts. One has a ו.
vav. Well, it seems like—yeah, I understand. But the גמרא Gemara is
going to say it's not just by chance that they had different
texts. There were, you know, it raises a question as soon as
you read the text. You're asking yourself, how do you parse this?
What does אינו מועד einu mu'ad mean? So we're going to see
that that was dealt with by the other evidence from the end
of the—from the other parts in the משנה Mishnah to indicate to
them how it should be—what either the גרסא girsa was or how
it should be parsed. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
רב זידא דייק מסיפא רב פפא דייק מרישא. Rav Zida dayek mi'seifa
Rav Pappa dayek mi'reisha. רב זיד Rav Zid learned it out from
the beginning of the משנה, Mishnah, רב פפא Rav Pappa from the
end. רב זידא דייק מסיפא. Rav Zida dayek mi'seifa. רב זיד Rav
Zid learns it out from the end of the משנה. Mishnah. דקתני
מועד לקטנים ואינו מועד לגדולים. de'ktani mu'ad liktanim ve'einu mu'ad ligdolim. Something
is a מועד mu'ad for קטנים ktanim and is not a מועד
mu'ad for גדולים. gedolim. Okay, which for him means that it saw
גדולים gedolim and it didn't gore them. אי אמרת בשלמא ואינו מועד
קתני, im amart bishlama ve'einu mu'ad ktani, that it's descriptive and it's
saying it happens to be that it's not a מועד mu'ad for
גדולים. gedolim. It saw גדולים gedolim and didn't gore them. הא סתמא
הוי מועד. ha stama havei mu'ad. So that would be implicitly telling
you that in a standard case, if it happened to gore three
small animals, we would assume it's a מועד mu'ad for everything, even
big ones. This was a case that it wasn't a מועד mu'ad
for big ones. It saw big ones and didn't gore them. But
a standard case, goring small ones, would be a מועד mu'ad for
everything, including big ones. Okay, הא סתמא—wait, ha stama
I lost my place—אינו מועד קטנים הא סתמא הוי מועד. einu mu'ad
ktanim ha stama havei mu'ad. הא קא משמע לן אפילו מקטנים לגדולים
נמי סתמא הוי מועד. ha ka mashma lan afilu miktanim ligdolim nami
stama havei mu'ad. So that's a חידוש. chiddush. The end of the
משנה Mishnah is telling you implicitly that if it gored small ones,
it would even—we would just assume it's a מועד mu'ad for everything,
even big ones, even though you would say, look, just because it
takes advantage, you know, bullies pick on the small guys, doesn't mean
it's going to pick on a big guy. Okay? So never—so that's
a חידוש. chiddush. It's telling you if it's a specific case that
it's not a מועד mu'ad for a גדול. gadol. But the standard
would be we would assume it would be a מועד mu'ad for
a גדול, gadol, even though that's a חידוש, chiddush, because even though
it only gored small ones. Okay? אלא אי אמרת אינו מועד קתני,
ela im amart einu mu'ad ktani,
but if the משנה Mishnah is telling you a הלכה, halakhah, if
it did X, it's not a מועד mu'ad for Y. סתמא לא
הוי
מועד, stama lo havei mu'ad, meaning just as the סתמא stama is,
if it did X, we don't extend it to Y. So השתא
יש לומר מקטנים לקטנים דעלמא סתמא לא הוי מועד. hasha yesh lomar
miktanim liktanim de'alma stama lo havei mu'ad. So the first part of
the משנה Mishnah is מועד למינו אינו מועד לשאינו מינו. mu'ad le'mino
einu mu'ad leshe'einu mino. If it gores oxen, it's not a... מועד
muad *muad* for goring sheep. Okay? So if it's gored a small
ox, it's not a מועד muad *muad* for goring small sheep. Okay?
So if that's true even from קטנים *ktanim* to קטנים *ktanim* you
don't transfer it, מקטנים לגדולים צריכא למימר *miktanim ligdolim tzricha l'meimar*, of
course then if you don't go from a small ox to a
small sheep, of course you wouldn't go from a small ox to
a big ox. Like you're not going to pick on something that's
not your own size, okay? So why would the משנה mishna *mishna*
have to tell me? Once you told me, it's telling me a
הלכה halacha? *halacha*, not a description. You don't go from מינו לשאינו
מינו *mino leshe'eino mino*, you don't go from small in מינו *mino*
to small in אינו מינו *eino mino*, of course you would never
go from small to big. So גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says no, not
necessarily. רב פפא Rav Pappa אמר לך איצטריך *Rav Pappa amar lach
itztrich*, no you need to tell me that. סלקא דעתך אמינא *salcka
da'atach amina* הוא פראי בהאי מינא פראי בהאי *hu parei behai mina
parei behai*. No, maybe you wouldn't go from small to small, from
small ox to small sheep, because you don't switch genres, you're only
interested in oxen. But maybe once you're goring in a certain מין
*min*, in an ox, הוא פראי בהאי מינא *hu parei behai mina*,
once you've breached that particular category, you're willing to attack oxen, פראי
בהאי *parei behai*, you're then you'll attack the whole category. לא שנא
גדולים Gedolim. דידיה ולא שנא קטנים דידיה *lo shna gdolim didei velo
shna ktanim didei*, won't matter small ones or big ones, קא משמע
לן ka mashma lan דלא הוי מועד muad. *ka mashma lan d'lo
havei muad*. It's telling you that it's not. So in each of
these there's a חידוש *chiddush*. You might say, you don't go from
small ox to small sheep, but I might think you go from
small ox to big ox. Maybe there's a certain degree of generalizing
or abstraction that we do, and the משנה mishna. *mishna* is telling
you you don't. You don't make any jumps. You don't jump from
oxen to sheep, you don't jump from small oxen to big oxen,
you don't jump from people to oxen, you don't make any jumps.
That's what רב פפא Rav Pappa *Rav Pappa* is reading that the
point of the משנה mishna: *mishna* is. אינו מועד eino muad תנן
*eino muad tnan*. Okay, now רב פפא Rav Pappa דייק מרישא *Rav
Pappa dayek me'reisha*. Now we're going to see where he gets the
strength of his position from, from the beginning of the משנה Mishnah.
*mishna*. דקתני *d'katani* מועד לאדם אינו מועד לבהמה Mu’ad l’adam eino mu’ad
l’beheima, *muad l'adam eino muad l'behema*. So again, it's telling you a
הלכה halacha? *halacha*, not a description. If something is a מועד לאדם
muad leadam *muad l'adam*, we do not generalize it to a בהמה
behama *behema*. That's how he reads it without the ו vav *vav*.
אי אמרת בשלמא אינו מועד eino mu’ad? תנן *ei amart b'shlama eino
muad tnan*, it's אינו מועד eino mu’ad. *eino muad* without the ו
vav, *vav*, סתמא לא הוי מועד muad *stama lo havei muad*. So
it's telling you that as a default, just because it gored אדם
adam *adam*, it's not going to, we don't assume it's going to
gore בהמה behama, *behema*. So that's a big חידוש *chiddush*. קא משמע
לן דאפילו מאדם לבהמה נמי סתמי לא הוי מועד muad *ka mashma
lan d'afilu me'adam l'behema nami stami lo havei muad*. That's a big
חידוש *chiddush*. Even if it gored people, you would think if it's
willing to gore a person, and people are better able to take
care of themselves and animals are more afraid of people, you would
think if it's willing to gore a person, it would certainly be
prepared to gore a בהמה behama *behema*. And it's telling you no,
even if it's a מועד לאדם muad leadam, *muad l'adam*, it's not
a מועד לבהמה muad lebehama. *muad l'behema*. That's a good way to
read the משנה Mishnah *mishna*. אלא אי אמרת ואינו מועד veino muad.
קתני *ela ei amart ve'eino muad katani*, and it's got the ו
vav, *vav*, הא סתמא הוי מועד muad *ha stama havei muad*. So
it's a מועד לאדם muad leadam *muad l'adam* and it happens to
not be a מועד לבהמה muad lebehama *muad l'behema*. It saw animals
and didn't gore them. The implication being that by default, מועד לאדם
muad leadam, *muad l'adam* is a מועד לבהמה muad lebehama, *muad l'behema*.
Okay? השתא יש לומר מבהמה לבהמה סתמא הוי מועד muad *hashta yesh
lomar m'behema l'behema stama havei muad*. So then that's like, why do
you have to tell me that? If you've already told me that
you would generalize from like oxen to a sheep, מועד muad, למינו
ואינו מועד veino muad, לשאינו מינו *muad l'mino ve'eino muad l'she'eino mino*,
it has to see sheep and not gore them to be a
not מועד muad. *muad* for a sheep. Otherwise, we assume a מועד
muad *muad* for בהמה behama *behema* is a מועד muad *muad* for
sheep. So then you don't have to tell me אדם adam *adam*
and בהמה behama *behema*. If it's willing to go from oxen to
sheep, it will certainly go from human beings to animals, because the
presumption is human beings are the hardest thing to gore, the thing
it's most afraid of. So once you're implicitly telling me you generalize,
according to רב זביד Rav Zvid *Rav Zevid*, from one type of
an animal to another, then why would you have to tell me
you generalize from a person to an animal? Okay? So השתא יש
לומר מבהמה לבהמה סתמא הוי מועד muad מאדם לבהמה צריכא למימר דהוי
מועד mu’ad *hashta yesh lomar m'behema l'behema stama havei muad me'adam l'behema
tzricha l'meimar d'havei muad*? Would you need to say that? ורב זביד
Zevid אמר לך בר זביד Zevid *V'Rav Zevid amar lach Bar Zevid*
will say to you, רישא אחזורתא *reisha achazorta*. You're right. When it
speaks about מועד לאדם muad leadam *muad l'adam*, מועד לאדם
ואינו מועד לבהמה muad leadam veino muad lebehama. *muad l'adam ve'eino muad
l'behema*, it doesn't have to tell me that you generalize from אדם
adam *adam* to בהמה behama. *behema*. That we could figure out, of
course you're going to do that. Here what it's telling you is
the, not the implication of what the standard case would be, but
to tell you the reality of how something becomes an אינו מועד
eino mu’ad, *eino muad*. What would that mean to be a מועד
לאדם muad leadam *muad l'adam* and an אינו מועד לבהמה eino muad
lebehama? *eino muad l'behema*? Here's the reality. כגון דהוה מועד לאדם muad
leadam, ומועד לבהמה *k'gon d'hava muad l'adam v'muad l'behema*.
Now for רב זביד Rav Zvid *Rav Zevid*, we would normally generalize.
But let's say you had an animal that actually, in practice, we're
not even generalizing, in practice, gored three people and gored three, three
cows. והדר ביה מבהמה *v'hadar bei m'behema*, and
then it saw three בהמות behemoth, *behemos* and it stopped goring. Okay?
דקאי גבי בהמה behama. תלתא זימני *d'kai gabi behema tlata zimni*, and
now it spells out for you what it means to revert. It
saw, it was presented, it was stood in front of בהמות Behemas.
*behemos* for three times. from ולא נגח and it didn't gore. So
maybe I would think in that case that becomes a, so the
משנה's Mishnah saying that's a מועד לאדם muad leadam, ואינו מועד veino
muad. לבהמה. How can something be an אינו מועד לבהמה? eino muad
lebehama. It could have reverted from בהמה behama because it saw it
three times and it didn't gore. מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, I might
say well maybe that should count as full תשובה. teshuva. If it's
not even goring בהמות, Behemas, it certainly won't gore an אדם, adam.
right?
So therefore מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, I might have thought כיון דלא
הדר ביה מאדם. keivan dela hadar bei meadam. I'm sorry, wait a
minute. מועד לבהמה והדר ביה מיניה דקאי קמי בהמה תלת זימנין ולא
נגח. muad lebehama vehadar bei mineih deqai qamei behama tlat zimnin velo
nagach. No, I'm sorry, it says the opposite. מהו דתימא, mahu deteima,
כיון דלא הדר ביה מאדם, keivan dela hadar bei meadam, חזרה דידיה
לאו חזרה היא. hazara dideih lav hazara hi. No, not the opposite
of what I said. Maybe I would say, look, it just reverted
from בהמה, behama. but we didn't see it yet revert from אדם.
adam So maybe
therefore, it's, and if it hasn't proven that it's given up goring
people, so maybe it has that viciousness that it's still going to
gore people. So then not goring בהמה behama. doesn't mean anything. It's
still like the worst criminal. And therefore, we're still going to make
it a מועד לבהמה. muad lebehama, קא משמע לן דחזרה בבהמה מיהא
חזרה היא. qa mashma lan dehazara bebehama miha hazara hi. No, we
will accept that it now has reverted from the בהמה behama and
it could be something could be in the status of being מועד
לאדם Muad le-adam, and אינו מועד eino mu’ad. לבהמה. It could revert
from בהמה behama and we don't view the fact that it has
not obviously reverted from אדם adam as evidence to discount the reverting
from בהמה. beheima, Okay. מיתיבי. meitivei. So it's getting a little complicated,
but we get the idea. That רב זביד Rav Zvid says in
general you generalize unless you have evidence that it's not. And רב
פפא Rav Pappa says you don't generalize. מיתיבי סומכוס אומר. meitivei Sumchus
omer. So now we have a ברייתא braita where סומכוס Sumchus disagrees
with the teaching of the משנה. Mishnah סומכוס Sumchus says
מועד לאדם מועד לבהמה מקל וחומר. muad leadam muad lebehama mikal vachomer.
No, no. If something's a מועד mu’ad לאדם, l’adam. it's going to
be a מועד לבהמה muad lebehama. from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
ומה לאדם מועד לבהמה לא כל שכן? uma leadam muad lebehama lo
kol shekein? It's so funny, it's like telling how it says קל
וחומר kal vachomer then it almost just doesn't clarify. It says it's
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If it's a מועד mu’ad for אדם
adam of course it's a מועד mu’ad for בהמה. beheima It's just
all in your tone of voice. Okay.
But what if he's just goring like little kids?
Oh that's a good question too. Right. But let's all assume same
size, okay? Anyway, so the point is that סומכוס Sumchus says if
it's a מועד mu’ad לאדם le-adam. of course it's a מועד לבהמה,
muad lebehama. which implies that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma was saying
if it's a מועד mu’ad לאדם, it's not a מועד לבהמה, muad
lebehama. meaning that the תנא Tanna was saying אינו מועד mu’ad stum,
not ואינו מועד. ve’eino mu’ad The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is making
a הלכתי halachic statement. מועד mu’ad לאדם does not make it a
מועד לבהמה. muad lebehama. Okay. So מכלל דתנא קמא אינו מועד קאמר.
miklal detanna kamma eino muad qa'amar. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
is going like רב פפא Rav Pappa, says. A מועד mu’ad לאדם
is not a מועד mu’ad לבהמה. You do not generalize. And סומכוס
Sumchus says I'm sorry, you do generalize, especially if it makes sense.
אמר ליה רב זביד סומכוס אחזרה קאי. amar leih Rav Zvid Sumchus
achazara qai. So רב זביד Rav Zvid says no, no, סומכוס Sumchus
is not discussing the initial becoming of a מועד. mu’ad Everybody would
agree if it's a מועד mu’ad לאדם, we generalize and it becomes
a מועד mu’ad? לבהמה. So what are we debating? We're debating whether
it can revert. Exactly what we just discussed a minute ago. והכי
קאמר ליה לתנא קמא דקאמרת חזרה דבהמה חזרה היא, vehachi qa'amar leih
letanna kamma deqamart hazara debehama hazara hi, what we just set up
as the case that it saw a בהמה three times and it
didn't gore it. And that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says establishes
it as a מועד mu’ad only for אדם adam, and not for
בהמה. So סומכוס Sumchus is saying I don't buy that תשובה. teshuva.
That תשובה teshuva is not sincere. Okay. חזרה דבהמה לאו חזרה היא.
hazara debehama lav hazara hi. No, if it didn't gore an animal,
that doesn't stop it from being a מועד mu’ad for בהמה. מקל
וחומר מאדם, mikal vachomer meadam, from a קל וחומר kal vachomer
from אדם. Adam. ומה מאדם לא קמהדר ביה, uma meadam lo qamahadar
bei, since it has not yet reverted from goring an אדם and
that's still in its place, so therefore the חזרה hazara for בהמה
doesn't mean anything.
אם עדיין הוא מועד לאדם לא כל שכן לבהמה. im adayin hu
muad leadam lo kol shekein lebehama. So what רב זביד Rav Zvid,
is saying certainly not פשט, pshat, but what רב זביד Rav Zevid.
is saying is everybody would agree that the starting is if it
becomes a מועד mu’ad for one, it becomes a מועד mu’ad, for
everything. מועד לאדם הוי מועד לבהמה. muad leadam havei muad lebehama. He
might even say מועד לבהמה הוי מועד לאדם. muad lebehama havei muad
leadam. Okay. You just generalize. So what's the debate of תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma and סומכוס? Sumchus? Because תנא קמא Tanna Kamma saying is
yes, but an animal could see a בהמה and revert from that.
And סומכוס Sumchus is saying no. If it's a מועד, mu’ad if
it's still a מועד mu’ad לאדם, it'll still be a מועד mu’ad,
לבהמה. That doesn't go away just by picking off the low-hanging fruit.
It still remains a מועד. Muad. But initially according to רב זביד,
Rav Zevid, if it becomes a מועד Muad for one, it becomes
a מועד Muad for everything. אמר רב אשי תא שמע. amar Rav
Ashi ta shema. Come and hear.
אמרו לפני רבי יהודה. ameru lifnei Rabbi Yehuda. They said to רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. The משנה: mishna. הרי שזה מועד לשבתות ואינו מועד
לימות החול. harei shezeh muad leshabatot veino muad leyimot hachol. What if
it's a מועד Muad for שבתות shabbosot and not for the weekdays?
אמר להם לשבתות משלם נזק שלם לימות החול משלם חצי נזק. amar
lahem leshabatot meshalem nezeq shalem leyimot hachol meshalem chatzi nezeq. Okay. Yes.
If that's what happened, it gored on שבת Shabbos and not on
the weekdays, then שבת Shabbos it pays full and weekdays it pays
half. אי אמרת בשלמא ואינו מועד קתני. i amart bishlama veino muad
qatani. If it's saying ואינו מועד, ve’eino mu’ad so they're laying out
a scenario. They're saying then here is the scenario. It gored on
שבת Shabbos and it didn't gore in the weekdays. What's the הלכה?
halacha? So that's ואינו מועד. ve’eino mu’ad, ואינו מועד Muad is they're
describing it. It gored on שבת, Shabbos, it didn't gore on the
weekdays, what's the הלכה? halacha. Okay. שיילו דקא משיילו ליה. Shayeilu d’ka
meshayelu lei. They're asking him in this scenario, what's the הלכה? halacha.
הוא נמי קא מהדר להו Hu nami ka mehadar lehu and he's
telling them, "Yes, if that's what happened, then we will treat it
as a מועד Muad on שבת Shabbos and not a מועד Muad
on the weekdays." אלא אי אמרת אינו מועד קתני, Ella ei amarta
eino mu’ad katani, but how would it read if it was אינו
מועד? Muad So what did they say to him? The students said
to רב יהודה: מועד לשבת אינו מועד לימות החול. Mu’ad l’Shabbos eino
mu’ad l’yamos hachol. So they're not asking him a question, they're just
saying a הלכה. halacha. מועד לשבת אינו מועד. Mu’ad l’Shabbos eino mu’ad.
And so then what's he responding? They're already teaching the same הלכה.
halacha. אגמורי הוא דקא מגמרי ליה. Agmurei hu d’ka megamrei lei. They're
teaching him a הלכה. halacha? It's not describing a case and asking
the הלכה. halacha If they're saying מועד לשבת אינו מועד לימות החול,
Mu’ad l’Shabbos eino mu’ad l’yamos hachol, that's a פסק. psak. ותוב איהו
מאי קא מהדר להו? V’tuv ihu mai ka mehadar lehu? What's he
responding to them? They already know the answer. אמר רב זביד: Amar
Rav Zevid: So therefore it's clear from the question that we're using
the ו and we're describing the scenario and and we're not saying
a פסק. psak. It's the ואינו מועד Muad describes it, it's not
a פסק psak אינו מועד. Muad אמר רב ינאי מרישא נמי דיקא.
Amar Rav Yannai meireisha nami deika.
You know what, you can also infer this from a close read
of the beginning of the משנה. mishna. דקתני את שמועד לו, D’katani
es shemu’ad lo, after it says, it's מועד Muad for X and
not מועד Muad for Y, מועד muad for this, not מועד muad
for that. And then it
says, את שמועד לו משלם נזק שלם ואת שאינו מועד לו משלם
חצי נזק. Es shemu’ad lo meshalem nezek shalem ve’es she’eino mu’ad lo
meshalem chatzi nezek. Right? That's how it ends after describing all the
cases. אי אמרת בשלמא ואינו מועד קתני, Ei amarta bishlama ve’eino mu’ad
katani, if you say ואינו מועד, muad פירושא קא מפרש לה. Peirusha
ka mefareish lah. So we describe the scenarios: something is a מועד
muad for אדם and not for בהמה, for big and not for
small, for this and not for that. What's the הלכה? halacha. The
הלכה halacha is the thing it's a מועד muad for pays full,
the thing it's not a מועד muad for pays half. Okay. Okay,
so that makes sense. אלא אי אמרת אינו מועד קתני, Ella ei
amarta eino mu’ad katani, but if it says אינו מועד, muad you
already told me the הלכה. halacha? מועד לאדם אינו מועד לבהמה, Mu’ad
l’adam eino mu’ad l’beheima, מועד למינו אינו מועד לשאינו מינו. Mu’ad l’mino
eino mu’ad l’she’eino mino. So if you're already, not the ו, you're
פסקן paskan already, פסקא פסקת, Piska piskat, you've already taught, it's פסק.
psak. You said if it's מועד muad. for this, it's not מועד
muad for that. מאי טוב את שמועד לו משלם נזק שלם ואת
שאינו מועד לו משלם חצי נזק? Mai tuv es shemu’ad lo meshalem
nezek shalem ve’es she’eino mu’ad lo meshalem chatzi nezek? So now if
you've already told me the פסק psak that it's a מועד muad
for this and not for that, why do you have to tell
me what the הלכה halacha is about a
מועד? muad הא עד השתא לא אשמעינן דהתם משלם חצי נזק ומועד
משלם נזק שלם? Ha ad hashta lo ashmeinan dehasam meshalem chatzi nezek
umu’ad meshalem nezek shalem? What? And we're already thirty-six דף daf into
this מסכת, masechet, I don't yet know the הלכה? Halacha? So if
you're telling me a פסק psak מועד לאדם אינו מועד לבהמה, Mu’ad
l’adam eino mu’ad l’beheima, you can stop there. You don't have to
tell me what the consequence of being a מועד and אינו מועד.
If you're describing it, something that is a מועד for has been
demonstrated to gore בהמה and not demonstrated to gore אדם or demonstrated
this and not that, then you have to tell me, "Okay, what's
the הלכה after that behavior has been demonstrated?" And so they'll tell
me, the thing it's habitual for is full, not habitual is half,
or shown that it's not habitual is half. But if it's a
ו, it's descriptive and then it ends with a פסק. psak. Here's
the פסק: psak: the thing it's evident, it's shown its habitual nature
for is full, not shown is half, or shown that it's not
habitual is half. But if you've already פסקן paskan מועד לאדם אינו
מועד לבהמה, so then you don't need that last line. ואם תימצי
לומר נמי איתא לרב פפא. Ve’im timtzi lomar nami isa l’Rav Pappa.
Okay, so anyway, so it sounds like the גמרא, Gemara you know,
the evidence of the end of the משנה mishna or the phrasing
of the משנה very heavily weights for רב זביד. Rav Zevid, Now
if it weights for רב זביד, Rav Zvid I gotta tell you,
it's going to make the rest of the גמרא Gemara very boring
because that's going to mean that in terms of how do you
determine what a pattern something establishes, for זביד it's like, it's never
a question. Like whatever, if it ever gores any three things, it's
a מועד for everything. The only question would be, did it actively
see certain things and didn't gore them? Right? But but to normally
determine what's the scope of it being a מועד, if it happened
to gore any three random things, we'll assume that it's a מועד
for everything. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is going to not want,
even though the evidence of the משנה is for רב זביד, Rav
Zvid. it's not going to want to give up רב פפא Rav
Pappa, because רב פפא Rav Pappa allows us to explore interesting questions.
Let's say it gored the following things, what type of a מועד
would it be? Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara now shifts
to. ואם תימצי לומר נמי איתא לרב פפא. Ve’im timtzi lomar nami
isa l’Rav Pappa. So even though we've pretty much disproven רב פפא,
Rav Pappa were we to פסקן paskan like רב פפא, Rav Pappa.
נגח שור חמור וגמל נעשה מועד לכל. Nagach shor chamor vegamal na’aseh
mu’ad lakol. If it gored a שור, shor, a חמור, chamor, and
a גמל, gamal, an ox, a donkey, and a camel, so for
רב פפא Rav Pappa you have to say, "What is the pattern?"
That's the question you ask yourself. We're only going to limit ourselves
to the evidenced pattern. For זביד it's everything, for רב פפא Rav
Pappa, we limit ourselves to the evidenced pattern. So what's the pattern
of שור חמור וגמל? shor chamor vegamal? So you could say nothing.
You could say you always, you always assume it's going to be
based on the type of thing it gored. Or you could say
no, no, no, we go to the to the level of abstraction
that allows us to find a common denominator. So in this case,
it would actually be, it wouldn't not be a מועד, this would
make it a מועד לכל. mu’ad lakol. Now, maybe not לאדם. Maybe
it wouldn't be a מועד. Now, maybe not לאדם. Maybe it's become
a מועד לאדם, or it would have to gore a שור חמור
shor chamor and then an אדם, right? You know, let's say the
שור חמור גמל shor chamor gamal were all baby animals, maybe it
wouldn't be a מועד for גדולים. Okay. So you go to the
smallest level of abstraction that contains everything that you've just seen. Okay.
Maybe it wouldn't be a מועד for goring chickens. Maybe it would
only be for בהמות. You know what I'm saying? So that's the
idea for רב פפא. Rav Pappa רב זביד Rav Zvid says you
just include everything. And רב פפא Rav Pappa says no, you include,
you go to the level of abstraction, the smallest category that allows
you to include all of the evidence that you've witnessed. All right,
so let's take a look. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: ראה שור נגח
שור לא נגח שור נגח שור לא נגח שור נגח שור לא
נגח, Ra'ah Shor Nagach Shor Lo Nagach, Shor Nagach Shor Lo Nagach,
Shor Nagach Shor Lo Nagach, נעשה מועד לסירוגין לשורים. Nasah Muad L'Shirugin
L'Shorim. If it alternated, okay, not on days, but it sort of,
you know, it gored every other ox that it saw, then it
would be a מועד for goring every other ox. So if it
was on off, on off, on off, then the next on would
be נזק שלם. Nezek Shalem. But if it did on on, then
the second on would be חצי נזק, Chatzi Nezek, okay, because it's
only habitual for every other ox. Okay. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: ראה
שור נגח חמור לא נגח סוס נגח גמל לא נגח פראד נגח
ערוד לא נגח. Ra'ah Shor Nagach, Chamor Lo Nagach, Sus Nagach, Gamal
Lo Nagach, Pered Nagach, Arod Lo Nagach. So it alternated, but it
was six different animals. Okay, so what's the pattern here? So, נעשה
מועד לסירוגין לכל. Nasah Muad L'Shirugin L'Kol. So again, according to רב
פפא, Rav Pappa. this is all, תוספות tries to work this in
with רב זביד. I'm not going to get into תוספות, but the
רי"ף Rif says that all these discussions are with רב פפא Rav
Pappa, because רב זביד generally assumes it's מועד for everything. Here it's
basically we're trying to make it a מועד for the smallest evidence
group. So that's the basis for the רי"ף Rif to say we
פוסקין Pasken like רב פפא Rav Pappa. because all these interesting questions
work easiest within רב פפא. Rav Pappa's So, for רב פפא, Rav
Pappa what is the smallest evidence group? So it's three different things
that it gored, so that basically means everything. Everything, I assume, means
all בהמות, presumably not אדם. But it only gored every other time,
so it is מועד to gore any type of an animal but
only on alternate
times. Okay. נעשה מועד לסירוגין לכל. Nasah Muad L'Shirugin L'Kol. איבעיא להו:
I'ba'ya Lehu: Now here's a question. נגח שור שור שור חמור וגמל.
Nagach Shor Shor Shor Chamor V'Gamal. So you have three of a
kind. Okay, not yet a full house. Okay. So what's the הלכה?
מהו? Mah-hu? Okay. האי שור בתר בתר שורים שדינא להו? Hai Shor
Battar Battar Shvarim Shadina Lehu? Do we say שור שור שור, Shor
Shor Shor, so that's after the first three, it was מועד לשורים?
Muad L'Shvarim? And then it had חמור Chamor and גמל, Gamal, well,
that's not going to make it מועד לכל, Muad L'Kol, because it
was מועד לשורים. Muad L'Shvarim. It would need to do maybe חמור,
Chamor, גמל, Gamal, and some third thing to be מועד לכל. Muad
L'Kol. Okay. וכיון דלשורים הוא דאייעד למיני אחריני לא אייעד? V'Kiyavanan D'Lishvarim
Hu D'Iyed L'Minei Acharinei Lo Iyed? It's only מועד for שורים, Shvarim,
not for all animals. או דלמא, Od Dilma, or do we say,
האי שור בתר בתר חמור וגמל שדינא ליה? Hai Shor Battar Battar
Chamor V'Gamal Shadina Lei? It was שור שור, Shor Shor, and then
it was שור חמור וגמל. Shor Chamor V'Gamal. So we look at
the last three, and the last three, the common denominator is all
animals. ואיעד ליה לכולהו מיני? V'Iyed Lei L'Kula Huminei? And then it's
for everything? So we don't know the answer. How about if it's
the reverse? חמור וגמל שור שור שור. Chamor V'Gamal Shor Shor Shor.
Okay. Now that way there's a better basis to say everything, because
the first three things that were witnessed establish a more general
pattern. מהו? Mah-hu? האי שור קמא בתר חמור וגמל שדינא ליה? Hai
Shor Kama Battar Chamor V'Gamal Shadina Lei? Do we put it after
the חמור Chamor and גמל? Gamal? So the first three gorings were,
you know, were of all different types and therefore it's מועד לכל.
Muad L'Kol. ואיעד ליה לכולהו מיני? V'Iyed Lei L'Kula Huminei? And it's
a מועד for all things. או דלמא, Od Dilma, or do we
say, בתר שורים שדינא ליה? Battar Shvarim Shadina Lei? No, nevertheless, if
you look at that grouping, חמור גמל שור שור שור, Chamor Gamal
Shor Shor Shor, they're drawn to the שור שור שור. Shor Shor
Shor. That's the most obvious consistent grouping. And therefore that determines that
it's a מועד לשורים. Muad L'Shvarim. וכיון דלשורים הוא דאייעד למיני אחריני
לא אייעד. V'Kiyavanan D'Lishvarim Hu D'Iyed L'Minei Acharinei Lo Iyed. Okay, so
we don't know the answer to that. Now, how about if it's
שבת שבת ושבת אחד בשבת ושני בשבת? Shabbat Shabbat V'Shabbat Echad B'Shabbat
V'Sheni B'Shabbat? שבת שבת שבת Shabbos Shabbos Shabbos Sunday Monday. Do we
say מהו? Mah-hu? הא שבת בתרא בתר שבת הוא דשדינא ליה? Ha
Shabbat Battra Battar Shabbat Hu D'Shadina Lei? Do we say שבת שבת
שבת, Shabbos Shabbos Shabbos, so after the first three times it's now
established itself as מועד for שבת? Shabbos? And then Sunday and Monday
is only two, two new events and not three new events and
not yet a new pattern. Okay. וכיון דלשבת הוא דאייעד לימי החול
לא אייעד? V'Kiyavanan D'Lishabbat Hu D'Iyed L'Yimei HaChol Lo Iyed? If it
did Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, then it would be everything. But at this
stage it's only for שבת, Shabbos, because three, the first three times
establish it as שבת. Shabbos. או דלמא, Od Dilma, or do we
say, בתר אחד בשבת ושני בשבת שדינא ליה? Battar Echad B'Shabbat V'Sheni
B'Shabbat Shadina Lei? No, we say we look at the last three,
which is שבת Shabbos Sunday Monday. And therefore we say it's a
מועד for all days of the week. Okay. ואיעד ליה לכולי יומי.
V'Iyed Lei L'Kulei Yomei. So we don't know. How about if it's
the first three, which is a more, a basis to say that
you go by the first three. ה בשבת וערב שבת ושבת. He
B'Shabbat V'Erev Shabbat V'Shabbat. Let's say it did Thursday Friday שבת, Shabbos,
and then שבת שבת. Shabbos Shabbos. Okay. So מהו? Mah-hu? What do
we say? הא שבת קמייתא בתר ה בשבת וערב שבת שדינא ליה?
Ha Shabbat Kama'ita Battar He B'Shabbat V'Erev Shabbat Shadina Lei? Do we
say once it did Thursday Friday שבת, Shabbos, it was a מועד
for all the days of the
week? Okay. ויעיד לכולי יומי ve-ya'id le-kulei yomei and then the fact
that the next two times are Shabbos doesn't reassess. We've established that
it's a מועד for all the days of the week. או דלמא?
o dilma? Do we say השבת כמעשה בשבת ושבת ושבת דשדינא ליה
ושבת ושבת דיעיד? Ha-Shabbos ke-ma'aseh be-Shabbos ve-Shabbos ve-Shabbos de-shadina lei ve-Shabbos ve-Shabbos
de-ya'id? No, we say when you look at that list, Thursday, Friday,
Shabbos, Shabbos, Shabbos, you're drawn to the Shabbos, Shabbos, Shabbos of the
most obvious grouping and it's only מועד for Shabbos. So we don't
know the answer to any of this, תיקו. teiku. Now, yes, I
can anticipate your question, Hillel, which is why don't we say it's
even if it was Shabbos, Shabbos, Shabbos, if it was Thursday, Friday,
Shabbos, it was Thursday, Friday, Shabbos and it was all the days
of the week, then the next time it gored was Shabbos, why
did not going on Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, and Friday undermine
its being a מועד for all the days of the week? Was
that your question? No. Okay, that's my question.
So I will say that we have to assume, that we would
have to assume it didn't see any ox during those days of
the week, right? If it was Thursday, Friday, Shabbos, Gemara thinks that
that might be a מועד for everything and then it was Shabbos,
Shabbos, but didn't it stop being a מועד for everything when it
went through the rest of the week and didn't gore? And the
answer is no, if it didn't see any animals for the rest
of the week that doesn't undermine its status. What was your question?
Right, that could be too, that could be too, it could have
been Sunday, Tuesday, Shabbos. But the point is, but in order that
the days between don't undermine it, you have to assume it was
not seeing ox during those interim days. Okay, let's get up to
the משנה.
We're going to get up to the משנה. נגח שור יום טו
בחודש זה יום טז בחודש זה יום יז בחודש זה. nagach shor
yom tes-vav be-chodesh zeh yom tes-zayin be-chodesh zeh yom yod-zayin be-chodesh zeh.
So it can also become a מועד the same. Now here, here's
where we become pure formalists. Because I, רש"י Rashi does this thing
of oh, Shabbos is different, it has a day off, people are
dressed differently. Here the גמרא Gemara, is assuming that if an ox
gores every sixteenth of every month for three months it gored on
the sixteenth, it's a מועד for going on the sixteenth, even though
that's like completely arbitrary. What made the sixteenth different? Okay, it's set
by the moon maybe. Anyway, but here's where it really seems we
become total formalists and we don't ask what would have led to
that, what's the causal relationship, we just say that's what's evidenced, that's
the status of it being מועד. So let's say instead of those
sixteenth, sixteenth, and sixteenth of three months, it did fifteenth, sixteenth, and
seventeenth of three successive
months, okay? פליגתא דרב ושמואל. pligta de-Rav u-Shmuel. That's a debate of
Rav and Shmuel because the point is like this: is it now
a מועד for doing the next month plus a day? The problem
is it has three months, they are in a pattern, fifteen, sixteen,
and seventeen, but the pattern of plus one only occurred twice, right?
Sixteen and fifteen was not a plus one pattern. Fifteen, sixteen, and
seventeen, sixteen and seventeen are only two times of having exhibited a
plus one pattern.
You could watch that ox and know what day of the month
it is.
Yes, that's true. Okay, דאתמר. de-itmar. It was taught, now this is
debated also by נדה Niddah and it's very interesting that the question
of establishing a pattern by the goring act, the וסת vesset means
a pattern, is a woman establishing a pattern of when she gets
her period so she knows which day she has to be concerned
that she will see her period. דאתמר. de-itmar. Right. ראתה יום טו
בחודש זה יום טז בחודש זה יום יז בחודש זה. ra'ata yom
tes-vav be-chodesh zeh yom tes-zayin be-chodesh zeh yom yod-zayin be-chodesh zeh. A
woman bled, got her period one month on the fifteenth, once on
the
sixteenth, and once on the seventeenth. רב אמר קבעה לה וסת. Rav
amar kave'ah lah vesset. She now has an established cycle and a
pattern that she'll see the next month plus a
day. Okay. ושמואל אמר עד שתשלש בדילוג. u-Shmuel amar ad she-teshalesh be-dilug.
No, no, she needs four months because she has to have three
months that have the plus one sort of experience. Okay, so anyway,
that's a debate of Rav and Shmuel. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. שמע
קול שופר ונגח קול שופר ונגח קול שופר ונגח. shama kol shofar
ve-nagach kol shofar ve-nagach kol shofar ve-nagach. If it heard a shofar
and it gored three times in a row, נעשה מועד לשופרות. na'aseh
muad le-shofaros. Then it's a מועד to gore every time it hears
a shofar. פשיטא. Pshita. Obviously. מהו דתימא. mahu de-teima. I might have
thought הכא שופר כמה סיוטא בעלמא הוא דנקטיה. hacha shofar kama siyuta
be-alma hu de-nakteih. Maybe the first shofar was just so like astounding,
like excited, bewildered, that it was really not that it's yet proven
habitual, that was like a more of an instinctive reaction. Of course
you could say all three times were an instinctive reaction but the
point is maybe the first time doesn't count. The first time it
was such a shock it gored as a result of that and
it doesn't yet establish this as a natural pattern. קא משמע לן
that no, we're still going to look at the three times. By
the end of the גמרא, Gemara certainly the גמרא seems against תוספות's
argument that not, it seems that it's working with רב פפא. Rav
Papa. רב פפא's certainly the more interesting position. The משנה says just
three times you just assume it's a מועד for everything. רב פפא
says no, no, no, we have to ask ourselves what is the
pattern? What is the smallest pattern that I can identify? That then
leads to interesting questions but it also seems that we've adopted a
lot of formalisms. We've dropped the idea that Shabbos is different because
people are dressed differently, fifteen 15, 16, 17 is a pattern for
days of the week plus one. Okay, we're not trying to really
explain any causal relationship. It now becomes an issue of like pattern
identification and that becomes now the approach within רב פפא. Yes.
And so there's an interesting
question like what counts as a pattern? It can't just be any
sequence of numbers. There's some sort of logic. So what is the
logic of a pattern? And so it would seem to me that
we should at least suggest that maybe a pattern is something that's
simple to describe, something like n, n plus 1, n plus 2
or n, n plus 2, n plus 4 or something like that,
but not 15, 117, 34. That wouldn't be a pattern.